In your name we pray, amen.
Well, good morning.
Good morning.
How's everybody doing?
How's everybody doing this morning?
Good.
Some people are good.
That's good.
I'm glad to hear that.
Hey, this morning we are launching a brand new series, as you can see, on the book of
Ruth.
I know all of you are very familiar with the story, right?
Because we all went to Sunday school growing up.
We know all the stories, right?
It's okay.
It's okay if you don't know all the stories.
That's totally fine.
That's what today is all about.
We're going to get to know the story a little bit.
I've been personally working through the book of Ruth over the past few months, and it is
slowly but surely becoming one of my favorite Old Testament books.
And so I'm really excited for us to work through it together.
And what I've noticed as I've been studying the book of Ruth is that there's many popular
level studies out there, books and sermons on the book of Ruth as of late.
And they've kind of boiled the book down, and maybe some of you that did grow up in church
have heard this version of the book of Ruth, but they've kind of boiled it down to like
this nice little love story that we kind of throw into the middle of like the action-packed
violence and genealogies of the Old Testament to give the readers a break, right?
Like, oh, like, take a breath.
Four chapters, love story.
This should be nice.
I actually heard one pastor call it the rom-com of the Old Testament.
Slightly disrespectful, in my opinion.
And I understand what these Bible teachers are attempting to do.
I don't hold anything against them or even think that some of the implications that they
are drawing out are wrong because they're not.
But I believe that underneath the surface of the story, there's far more depth and nuance
and biblical significance in the book of Ruth than we might realize.
And if we are going to boil it down to a love story, we should at least compare it to the
likes of Pride and Prejudice, which is undebatably an incredible love story with depth and nuance
and meaning.
And if you don't agree with me, find another church.
No, I'm kidding.
I'm kidding.
But seriously, who doesn't like Pride and Prejudice?
And the story of Ruth is perfect for the season of Lent.
If you don't know, we're in the second Sunday of Lent.
And I won't make you all raise your hands if you have already failed in your Lenten fasting
because I don't want to embarrass myself.
Come on, guys.
I wrote that joke this morning while we were doing worship.
I thought it was going to be good.
All right.
Anyway.
No, it's a great book for the season of Lent.
And we actually intentionally put it in the season of Lent for this reason,
that we are invited into the desert.
Of life with Ruth and Naomi in the book of Ruth.
We get to walk with them through the pits of despair and see God at work in a process of redemption in their lives.
It's a book about grief and lament, hope and restoration.
And it invites us to wrestle with God through the painful seasons of our own lot.
It helps us to see how God might invite us to participate in his process of redemption moving forward.
So, let's pray and then we'll just see how far we get.
Sound good?
All right.
Father in heaven, we thank you for this time that we have focused our attention on the throne room of heaven,
reminded ourselves of your holiness, reminded ourselves, God, that you are totally set apart,
seated on the throne, seated on the throne, high and lifted up.
That you are worthy of our praise and attention, our questions, our doubts, our fears, our anxiety.
You are worthy of it all.
And you're not afraid of it.
God, you welcome our wrestling and our struggles and our fear.
And the answers that you do give us are sufficient to help us persevere in this life of chaos and sorrow.
And God, when you lovingly and wisely choose not to give us answers because we wouldn't understand them,
you comfort us in the midst of our questions and our doubt.
That's really what Ruth is all about.
So help us to see, help us to see you on every page of this book.
Help us to see how you are interacting with the chaos of our own lives as we see you interact with the chaos of Ruth and Naomi.
God, draw near to us and comfort us.
And if we're not suffering, give us encouragement to come alongside those who are.
To help them endure and persevere and cling to you by faith.
I pray all of this in the name of Jesus.
Amen.
So date nights look a little bit different for Marissa and I now that we have almost two-year-old.
First, they're less frequent than they used to be.
And second, we've had to find some creative ways to go about doing them.
And one of our favorite new creative ways to have a date night is that after Rory goes to bed, we bust out these murder mystery board games.
Have any of you seen or played with the murder mystery board games?
A couple of you?
All right.
Yeah.
They are, in my opinion, a tremendous amount of fun.
They're more fun for Marissa because she's better at it than I am.
She grew up on Agatha Christie and I grew up on the Left Behind series.
So she's a bit better at looking for the nuanced clues and details.
But the way it works is you get thrust into the middle of a crime scene.
You're introduced to some characters and to the plot.
And you're just kind of sifting through all these different clues.
And you're trying to build a case.
You're trying to piece together the clues to build the most plausible case for who committed the murder and why.
There's actually, the ones that we get, there's a lot of nuance and detail.
And you could get all of the clues and unpack it and build your case.
And you're still not totally sure it's the person you think it is, right?
Like, there's usually two or three possibilities that you really have to work through.
And then kind of at the end say, like, pretty sure it's this person and here's all of the reasons why building the case.
And then you have to just, by faith, plug in the answer and see if you won the game night or not.
We have yet to lose, mostly, again, because Marissa grew up on Agatha Christie.
So I'll give her all the credit for that.
But the reason I share this story is because in a lot of ways, this is how each one of us as individuals living on a broken world,
living in a fallen world in the midst of suffering and chaos and difficulty and the grind of everyday life,
in a lot of ways, this is how we all build the case for our own meaning and significance.
We're just plopped into the middle of creation in our little sphere in Frederick County with all of the experiences that we have.
And we're trying to make sense of the world.
Why are we here?
How did we get here?
What does this all mean?
What is my purpose for being here?
And philosophers call this idea, this building the case for your life, they call this a worldview.
And you guys went to college.
You probably had a philosophy class about worldview.
Am I the only one?
I know just enough about philosophy and worldview to make a fool out of myself this morning.
So this should be fun.
So whether you know it or not, we all have one.
We all have a worldview.
And a worldview is a set of assumptions that we as individuals have kind of put in place to interpret our life.
It is the case we build to make sense of the details of our life, to put us into a broader story.
It's the underlying answers we believe about the most fundamental questions of reality, like where did we come from, why are we here, and what happens to us after we die.
It helps us make sense of complex situations.
Now, many of us in the room likely have what we would call a biblical worldview.
That's not all one size fits all, right?
There's not just one biblical worldview.
But most of us have some version of a biblical worldview where we look to the Scriptures, to the life and teachings of Jesus, and to creation to answer these big questions about life, to build the case for why we're here and what this whole thing is all about.
Whether you hold to a biblical worldview or not, the reality is most of us are likely influenced by, or if you grew up in the type of church that I grew up in,
reacting against the secular worldviews of the day.
None of that is bad.
It's just important to understand that we've likely been influenced or reacting against popular worldviews of the day.
The two most prominent that many of you would probably be familiar with is the modern worldview and the postmodern worldview.
Somebody shake your head if you know these words.
Okay, cool.
Some of us do, and the rest of us are going to get one of the worst summary lessons they've ever heard.
The modern worldview, it comes out of the Enlightenment and the technological revolution,
and it puts all of its confidence in science, logic, and reason to answer life's toughest questions.
It says, we can figure out the answers to our most complex questions.
We have it inside of us.
With science and logic and reason, we can figure it out.
This worldview is famously summarized by the quote by Nietzsche.
He said, God is dead, and we killed him.
This is a worldview moving away from all spiritual realm and just saying, we can figure out.
We can figure out the answers to the questions that we need with our hands and with our minds.
We'll figure it out.
The postmodern worldview did what many young generations are known for.
I don't know if you know this about young generations, but we swing pendulums to the extreme side of where our parents were.
It's super healthy and great, and it always works out.
So then it just ends up the older generation and the younger generation are just both wrong,
and we're like yelling at each other from opposite sides of the pendulum.
But the postmodern worldview swung the pendulum and was rightly skeptical of the overconfidence boasted by the modernists,
and they built their worldview on skepticism.
They sought to tear down all absolute truth claims.
Truth is a subjective experience.
We can all make sense of our own story on our own.
There doesn't have to be a grand narrative that makes sense of all of human existence.
You've probably heard the phrase, live your truth.
That is kind of the mantra of the postmodern worldview.
Now, we live in a really interesting time where many philosophers and sociologists think that there is a crisis of worldview.
Many people, and we can know this for a couple of different reasons.
First is many people with a biblical worldview are deconstructing their worldview,
either completely or, and walking away from the church.
You guys probably know, every one of us in here probably knows somebody who grew up with a biblical worldview.
And because of the answers that they got for their toughest questions said,
yeah, this isn't doing it for me.
I'm going to walk away from the church altogether.
That's kind of the worst case scenario.
Many others are deconstructing their biblical worldview and rebuilding one that is a bit more nuanced and complex
and can handle some of the more difficult questions of life.
And those outside the church seem to be, the younger generation seems to be discontent with the modern view
and the postmodern view, and they're trying to find some new version of a worldview that answers their toughest question.
Now, the reason for this brief and oversimplified philosophy lesson is to say this.
I think that Christians and non-Christians alike are sick of oversimplified answers to nuanced questions.
We're sick of being given answers that don't satisfy the longings of our hearts.
The overconfidence of modernism has failed us.
The subjectivity and deconstruction of postmodernism left us outside a house that we destroyed in ruins.
And the oversimplified and sentimental biblical worldview comes up short.
We often, as a church, we take the Bible and we use it to create oversimplified and unhelpful answers to nuanced and difficult questions.
And people are unsatisfied with the ways in which we are answering the most difficult question.
But, as a person who started this pendulum swing in his own journey and began to deconstruct some of the unhelpful answers to questions that I found,
the more I study, the more confident I have become that the Bible is the story that we are all looking for.
It is complex and it is beautiful.
It gives us the answers that we need to our most challenging questions,
and it comforts us in the midst of the questions it doesn't sufficiently answer.
It gives us what we need.
It doesn't give us everything that we want, but it gives us what we need.
And the God of all comfort meets us in the midst of our questions.
And the book of Ruth is a summary of the entire biblical story in a singular book.
It's a test case.
We get a test case into this one family and we get to see them interact with the worldview of the Bible.
As they are thrust into difficult circumstances, as they suffer and wrestle with the realities of living in a broken creation,
we get to see them wrestle with God.
And we get to see how the grand narrative of Scripture makes sense of their suffering and their sorrow.
It gives us a look into how the story of one family interacts with the story of the Bible,
and it invites us to walk alongside of them and see how the story of the Bible might make sense of each one of our stories,
each one of the difficulties of life that we face.
Every question that we might have, we can begin to see how God interacts with Ruth and Naomi in the midst of their questioning and doubt.
One pastor I really like says it this way.
He says, the book of Ruth is the story of the whole Bible told through three characters in four chapters.
It really is this grand narrative, this worldview, this biblical worldview kind of played out through the life of Ruth and Naomi and Boaz,
which we won't get to today.
We'll get to Boaz later.
But for now, Ruth and Naomi.
So my goal for today is to just set the book up, to show you how it works as an overview,
and then we'll spend the next few weeks leading up to Easter to kind of work through it in more detail.
Does that sound like a plan?
Awesome.
Thank you for following along with my generic value version of philosophy class this morning.
I'm trying to think of a way to make it sound better than that.
All right, Ruth chapter one, verse one.
In the days when the judges ruled in Israel, a severe famine came upon the land.
So a man from Bethlehem in Judah left his home and went to live in the country of Moab,
taking his wife and his two sons with him.
The names, the man's name was Elimelech.
Look to your neighbor and say, Elimelech.
It's fun to say, isn't it?
And if you don't like your neighbor, you can accidentally spit while saying Elimelech.
And we can see how pacifist we are in the room this morning.
The man's name was Elimelech and his wife's name was Naomi.
Their two sons were Malon and Kilion, and they were Epaphrodites from Bethlehem in the land of Judah.
And when they reached Moab, they settled there.
Then Elimelech died, and Naomi was left with her two sons.
The two sons married Moabite women.
One married a woman named Orpah, the other Ruth.
But about ten years later, both Malon and Kilion died.
This left Naomi alone without her two sons or her husband.
You guys hoping to be encouraged this morning?
This is the reality of life in a broken world.
And the author of Ruth doesn't waste any time to set up the plot of the story.
We immediately see an Israelite family doing their best to survive.
This is a family that finds themselves in the nation of God's chosen people.
Right?
Life should be good for God's chosen people.
But that's not what we see in the first few verses of the book of Ruth.
And it's often not what those of us who follow Jesus faithfully experience as our own life.
Israelite family was doing their best to survive and struggle.
And we're struggling in a world where life isn't going as they thought it would.
Anybody resonate with that story?
You can see a lot of parallels.
For those of you that are familiar with Job,
there's a lot of parallels between the book of Ruth and the book of Job immediately.
Naomi and her family.
Naomi and Ruth are left with nothing.
Left to wrestle with God and try and figure out how to make sense of all of this.
The author of Ruth gives us a setting to understand where we're at in the grand narrative of Scripture.
They say,
In the days the judges ruled.
Again, if you went to Sunday school growing up, you know this.
But for those of us who didn't,
this seven-word phrase is packed with cultural context for the original recipients.
It would be like me saying to you as I turned on the news that morning, September 12th, 2001.
Right?
It carries with it like cultural understanding of what was happening in that day.
All of us that lived through that day are immediately transported back to what our experience was like.
And those of us who are too young to be alive at that point,
you've heard enough stories where you can, in your mind's eye, imagine yourself in that cultural setting.
And this is what the author of Ruth does.
She sets us in the context of the book of Judges.
We're transported to this time where one generation after Joshua leads the nation of Israel into the promised land.
Right?
So we've got God bringing the Israelites out of slavery in Egypt, wandering in the wilderness for 40 years.
Joshua brings the people of Israel into the promised land.
And one generation after Joshua, we read this in the book of Judges,
an entire generation grew up that did not acknowledge God or remember the things that he has done.
What do we say about younger generations swinging the pendulum?
Right?
We have a generation of people who wrestled with God in the wilderness and through miraculous power
were brought into the land that they had been promised as they were waiting for 400 years in slavery.
God delivers them.
He does the thing he promised to do.
And one generation later, we have an entire group of people who have totally left and forsaken God,
totally ignored what God has done for them and is doing for them.
This was their response.
At the very end of the book of Judges, we can read a summary statement of how this entire generation lived.
It says,
in those days, in the days the judges ruled, Israel had no king and everyone did what was right in their own eyes.
They ignored their relationship with God and his laws and once again began to define good and evil for themselves.
Sound like another time in Scripture that we might be familiar with?
Right?
It's this cycle.
It's this pattern of human existence.
God shows up, invites us into relationship with himself.
We rebel and choose to define good and evil for ourselves.
And when we do that, chaos and suffering follow.
They ignored their relationship with God and his laws, defined good and evil for themselves.
They worshiped false gods and their idolatry through the entire nation into chaos and disorder.
Throughout the book of Judges, we see what theologians call the judges cycle.
Where they rebel, define good and evil in their own eyes.
They do what they want to do, how they want to do it.
Sound like anybody you're familiar with?
We just talked about postmodernism, right?
Postmodernism is in some ways a reliving of the cycle of the judges.
We can do whatever we want.
We can define good and evil for ourselves.
How's that work?
All right.
Good.
We see this cycle, right?
We see this cycle where they do what is right in their own eyes.
It leads to suffering and chaos and they're stubborn.
And so they muscle it out for as long as they can.
And then they say, okay, I guess we'll repent and we'll ask God for forgiveness.
And he raises up a judge who delivers them from their suffering and their chaos.
And as soon as they get comfort, as soon as they get relief from their suffering and their chaos,
they turn back to doing whatever is right in their own eyes.
This is the judges cycle.
And this is the setting for the book of Ruth.
And I think it helps us to kind of zoom out and see an underlying principle that is true of God's grand narrative.
Remember we said the book of Ruth helps us to zoom out and see how God's story interacts with our story.
And there is a reality that is true in God's world.
It's true in nuanced explanation.
Some people try and oversimplify this and use it for their own good.
But I would say this, that submission to God leads to life and flourishing.
Rebellion against God leads to chaos and suffering.
This is a reality of the biblical narrative from the beginning, from Genesis chapter one.
And God is inviting people to submission to him as the Lord and leader, as the creator who deserves their worship.
He's inviting us to partner with him.
And when we partner with him, we get something called Eden, which is abundance and life.
But when we choose to rebel against God, we get something called east of Eden, life outside of the Garden of Eden, which leads to chaos and suffering.
Adam and Eve chose to rebel, which thrust the world into chaos and suffering.
But God does not give up on the human project.
Remember we talked about a couple weeks ago, the way that he defines himself before the people of Israel.
He says, Yahweh is compassionate and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love.
It's the very character and nature of God, that he does not give up on us, that he slowly and patiently draws us back into relationship with himself, inviting us to partner with him.
And when we choose to partner with him, we get life and flourishing.
Now, this is where I want to say that it's nuanced, because this is not prosperity gospel stuff, right?
This is not do the right thing, give the right amount of money, pray the right prayers, and everything in life goes well.
This is more like what Jesus defines as abundant life, and he tells his disciples who are about to be martyred for following him, that they can have abundant life if they trust him.
So abundant life does not necessarily mean what we think when we think life and flourishing.
But if we can, by faith, just cling to the God who defines good and evil,
if we can repent from our original decision to define good and evil for ourselves,
and trust that he knows what he's doing when he says,
trust me and it will lead to life flourishing,
then just maybe we can get some reprieve, some redemption in the midst of our suffering.
The nation of Israel is this partnership between a person and God.
God invites Abraham to partner with him, to submit to him, and to have life and abundance in his name.
In the book of Genesis, everyone is moving away from Eden.
As you read Genesis 1 through 11, like every single person is moving away from God,
eastward, away from Eden, and God grabs Abraham and he says,
will you trust me and will you move west?
Will you come back with me?
And if you will, I will create a nation for you.
And this nation will be this project of human partnership with God.
And in some ways, it's Adam and Eve's partnership with God restored for the nation of Israel.
And he's going to set up the tabernacle, which becomes like a miniature version of Eden in the midst of Israel.
And he's saying that if you partner with me, if you trust me, I will bring about Eden,
even in the midst of chaos, in the chaos of your life.
It doesn't mean the chaos outside goes away.
It means that he brings Eden to us in the midst of our chaos.
So as God brought the nation of Israel into their promised land,
he set up some ground rules for their partnership.
In Deuteronomy chapter 28, he says,
if you obey me, you will experience blessing and abundance.
You will experience Eden.
If you disobey me, you will experience judgment and famine.
All right.
Now, the worst reading of this, for those of you that are skeptical about a biblical worldview,
the worst reading of this turns God into a cosmic dictator in the sky on a power trip.
Anybody have friends who would say they read the Old Testament and that's the God they see?
Okay.
I don't necessarily, like, judge them for that.
Let's help them, again, give a nuanced explanation of what's going on.
But a proper reading is that God created everything and knows how creation is intended to function.
His laws represent and summarize this.
His law is summarized by love of God and love of neighbor.
And if you really dig into God's law, as we will throughout the book of Ruth,
you will see that the laws that he gave the people of Israel run in contrary to the power structures of this world that lead to chaos and death.
The law is summarized and pays special attention to the most vulnerable people.
And it invites leadership that is rooted in humility and sacrificial service.
If you read the description of kings that God gives in Deuteronomy, of the type of king that should rule Israel,
it's a king who isn't collecting a bunch of power, who isn't collecting a bunch of money,
but who is distributing wealth to God's people so that they can be a testimony to who God is to the rest of the world.
It runs in contrary to how we run nations today.
The way I always illustrated this for my youth group students was, it was always fun.
I would have a board, a two by four, with a couple of nails, and I would have them race to hammer the nail into the board.
One of them would get a hammer.
Another would get like a boulder.
Another would get a brick, right?
And it's like, okay, like, go, race.
Try to get this nail in this board.
You guys know what happened, right?
The person with the hammer won.
And the person with the rock and the brick sometimes bruised the fingernail, cut open their skin.
Like, it was awesome.
I got lots of calls from parents.
But the reality is, like, God created us.
He knows how life is intended to work.
And when he gives us tools and definitions for right and wrong,
it's not because he's a cosmic dictator on a power trip,
but it's because he knows how the thing works.
And he's invited us to partner with him and do it the way that he's called us to do it.
And we can do it in other ways.
We can live life in other ways.
And, like, you can hammer a nail with a rock or with a brick,
but it often does some damage to you.
It does some damage to the wood.
It does some damage to the nail.
Like, there are consequences for doing things in a way that is not in line with the design.
And that's how creation functions.
After the fall, the nation of Israel is functioning,
this way in the time of judges.
They are trying to cultivate God's creation in a way that leads to life and flourishing,
but they are using their own definitions, their own tools, and their own strength.
And this will always ultimately lead to chaos and suffering.
We see that immediately in this text.
Israel had a severe famine come upon the land.
This family in Bethlehem had no food.
The land of Israel was described as this land flowing with milk and honey.
The name Bethlehem literally means the house of bread.
And so because God's people rebelled against God and chose to live life their own way,
based on their own definitions and their own understanding,
now we go from them being brought into the land flowing with milk and honey,
into the house of bread,
and now we see there is no food in the house of bread,
in the land flowing with milk and honey.
This is life outside of Eden.
This is creation experiencing the consequences of living apart from God.
Now there's, again, to be nuanced,
there's three major categories of chaos and suffering that all of us face from time to time.
The first is our consequences of decisions that we have made ourselves.
All of us at times rebel against God.
We choose right and wrong for ourselves.
We make decisions apart from God and we suffer the consequences of those decisions.
The second is many of us know the pain of suffering consequences from decisions of others.
Somebody else decides to do something that is in rebellion to God,
that apart from God,
and they're in proximity to you and that decision leads to your chaos and suffering.
Those of you with parents who have substance abuse understand this type of suffering.
Those of you who have experienced sexual abuse as children understand this type of suffering.
Many of us in the room have suffered because of the consequences of others.
Poverty, abuse, racism, injustice,
all of this is suffering that we have experienced because of the decision of others.
And the last and the one that's the hardest for all of us to reconcile,
is living in a broken world.
Some of us just suffer what seems indiscriminate suffering because we live in a broken world.
Natural disasters, mental health struggles, cancer, infertility, and on and on we could go.
There's something that just doesn't make sense about good people suffering consequences in this world.
And the reality is all of us in this room have likely suffered one or many of these.
However, I think the temptation we often face when suffering any of these is to turn our pain and anger towards God.
We want Him to erase the consequences of our mistake.
Totally, completely, scot-free.
God, I'm sorry, eliminate it.
But, how do we want God to treat people who have sinned against us?
Swift and merciless judgment to those who have sinned against us.
And we can't, we cannot reconcile how a good and powerful God would seemingly let indiscriminate suffering fall upon His creation.
That's why I had Josh read that passage in 2 Peter.
Because I think what we see as God, a good and powerful God, letting indiscriminate suffering happen,
is actually God's patient invitation to all of His creation.
Yes, we live in a broken world where there is suffering that doesn't always make sense.
But the reason it's dragging out this long is because God is compassionate and gracious.
He's slow to anger and He's abounding in steadfast love.
And He's inviting more and more people to surrender their lives,
to give up on their own definitions of good and evil, and to turn to Him.
And so sometimes good people, people who are faithful to God,
they suffer in the midst of the brokenness of this world.
And you're like, why?
They didn't do anything.
Nothing was done to them.
But what if God is just patiently inviting us to surrender to Him,
to trust Him, and to wait for His redemption?
Which leads me to my next logical question,
and I have to move fast because I'm going way slower than I intended to go.
What about Elimelech suffering?
Look at your neighbor again and say Elimelech,
and spit in their face if you don't like them.
Kidding.
Don't do that.
Is Elimelech suffering because of decisions that he made,
or because of the decisions of others,
or just because he lives in a fallen, broken world?
Now, this is where, again, I think we can begin to see the complexities
of how the biblical story interacts with our story.
Because I think it'd be really easy to say,
well, Elimelech's obviously suffering the consequences of his own decisions.
Right?
He lives in Israel.
Everyone in Israel is doing what's right in their own eyes,
and that is leading to suffering and pain.
I, however, and I could be wrong,
I heard a pastor once say,
this is not helping me speed up when I say things that aren't in my notes,
but I heard a pastor say once that he thinks like 80 to 90%
of everything he says on Sundays are right,
and the other 10 to 20% is wrong.
The problem is he's just not sure which percentage is wrong,
or he wouldn't say it.
So, I could be wrong here, but I have a theory,
and my theory is that I don't think Elimelech and his family's story
is as simple as we like to make it look.
See, people look at Elimelech's story,
and they say, okay, he's in the nation of Israel.
Everyone is doing what's wrong, or what's right in their own eyes,
and that's why they're suffering the consequences of life,
in a broken world.
But I think it's possible that up to this point,
up to the point where they had a famine,
I think it's actually likely, even probable,
that Elimelech and his family were a part of a minority of Israelites
that remained faithful and obedient to God
in the midst of the nation in rebellion.
Like, you read the words,
everyone in Israel did what was right in their own eyes,
and like, that's a literary device, right?
That doesn't actually mean every single individual,
there's not a single faithful person in the nation of Israel
in the story of Judges.
That's not true.
I think about the story of Elijah, right?
Where Elijah goes to battle with the prophets of Baal,
and he wins, and he has this victory,
and then he's on the run from his enemy,
and he's confronted God.
He's like, God, I am the only person in Israel
who remained faithful to you.
Sometimes it feels like that,
but God laughs at him as like,
yeah, I got like 7,000 other people
who haven't bent the knee to the Baal.
Right?
Like, it's not just you.
I know it feels like just you.
And so I think that there's a minority group of people
in the time of Judges who remained faithful to God.
And the reason I think that's true about Elimelech
is one, because the meaning of his name.
Elimelech's name means,
my God is king.
And if you look at every other name in the book of Ruth,
it's spot on with the character that they play in the story.
It's like identical to what they do in the story.
Some examples, Malone and Kilion died in the first five verses.
You want to know what their names mean?
Sicko and done for.
Right?
Naomi, her name means refreshment,
and it's a synonym of Eden.
And later, after Naomi comes back to Israel
and she wrestles with God,
she tells her friends,
don't call me Naomi,
don't call me refreshment,
don't call me Eden,
call me Mara,
call me suffering,
call me chaos.
Right?
So she's playing on this thing.
The names in the story give a lot of meaning.
Ruth means friendship.
And as we are going to see throughout the book,
Ruth is an incredible friend to Naomi.
So I think Elimelech's name,
meaning my God is king,
demonstrates to me,
at least in this story,
that it's possible he's remaining faithful to God
up to the point of this famine.
The other thing that tips it off to me
is throughout the book of Ruth,
you're going to see Ruth
have a tremendous amount of knowledge
about the law and character of God.
And Ruth is a Gentile woman
who grew up with no experience
or understanding of God's work.
She lived in Elimelech's household for 10 years.
She comes back to Israel
and demonstrates an incredible amount of knowledge
about God's work,
about the character of God.
And so I think,
I think Elimelech is doing his best
to remain faithful to God
amidst the generation
that is totally rebellious to God.
But when his back is against the wall,
when his family has no food to eat,
he gives in.
He makes a practical decision
over a decision that aligns
with his spiritual identity.
And I can't help but wonder.
See, Moab is a place
that the Israelites had no business going to.
No matter how bad it was,
God was inviting them
to live in the promised land.
And Moab and Israel don't mix.
It's like going to your nation's enemy,
a nation that is totally,
totally idolatrous
and has nothing to do with the God of Israel.
And so Elimelech makes this decision,
this practical decision
to try and keep his family alive.
And I think he turns his back
on his spiritual identity.
I can't help but wonder
how many of us have done
or are doing similar things.
We would say Jesus is the Lord of our lives,
but if you look at the decisions we make
when our backs are against the wall
or when we're facing difficulty,
they demonstrate that we value our own comfort,
the opinions of others
or the pressure to give our kids
the same life their friends have
more than we do submitting to
and trusting Jesus
as the Lord of our lives and our family.
Elimelech demonstrates half-hearted obedience.
And that half-hearted obedience
is so true of so many of us.
And what's disheartening to me
is that his sons pick up on his value system.
They, in turn, make pragmatic decisions
when in Moab,
when it's time for them to get married,
when they should be marrying Israelite women,
the law actually commands Israelite men
not to marry Moabite women.
The children make a pragmatic decision.
There's no need for them to walk back to Israel
to find wives.
They'll just find wives in Moab.
Fathers, mothers,
the value system that we model
and demonstrate to our children
will carry into their lives.
Do we just say that Jesus is the Lord of our lives?
Or do we actually live that way
even when our backs are up against the wall?
That was not the main point of my sermon
and we are almost done.
So let's keep going.
If we zoom out a bit,
we can begin to see how the story of Ruth
is more than just the story of one family,
but the story of the whole Bible.
We see from the beginning pages of Ruth,
there's rebellion against God
that leads to suffering and death.
It actually leads to three primary consequences.
If you read the first five verses of Ruth again,
you will see that there is a struggle for food,
a struggle for family,
and death.
Bible scholars,
anybody remember those three consequences?
Genesis 3.
These are the three primary consequences
of rebellion against God.
From the beginning to now,
it keeps happening.
When we rebel against God,
we'll have a struggle for food,
we'll have a struggle for family,
and we'll have death itself.
This is the story of human experience.
If you live long enough,
you will wrestle with all three.
Throughout the story of Ruth
and the Bible,
God is inviting people out of this cycle.
We don't have to keep wrestling with God
or doing what is right in our own eyes.
We can trust him to redeem us
through the midst of our suffering
and chaos in this broken world.
This is my main point
that I got to way too late.
God will bring redemption
in the midst of chaos and suffering
to anyone who clings to him in faith.
This is the story of Ruth.
This is the story of the Bible.
This is the invitation of God.
We live in a broken world
with chaos and suffering,
some of which we brought on ourselves,
some of which are brought on by others,
and some of which are just
the seemingly unfortunate things
that happen when we live in a broken world.
Now, this is a great main point for a sermon,
if I do say so myself.
The problem is it's oversimplified, right?
These are the type of answers
that we have given people forever,
and it's the reason why so many people
have walked away from the story of Scripture
because we haven't allowed the nuance to play out.
And that's why I love the book of Ruth
because even though we see at the beginning
and the end of Ruth
that this is the ultimate grand narrative,
it does not erase the suffering in the middle.
It does not explain it away.
The grand narrative of Scripture,
the redemption of God,
does not explain away our suffering
or try and tell you not to feel it
or not to hate it.
God grieves in the midst of the suffering
of his broken creation.
It is not something that is wrong for us
to grieve or be angry with
or be frustrated by.
I heard one Jewish scholar say it this way,
in the Jewish culture,
questions are as sacred as answers
because they are confident
that the biblical narrative
is strong enough to be tried and tested.
We have to get better at this church.
We have to allow people who are wrestling
with the suffering and chaos
of living in a broken world
with people who have suffered the consequences
of their own horrible decisions,
the horrible decisions of others
or the horrible effects
of living in a broken world,
we have to let them wrestle.
We cannot offer trivial answers
to difficult, nuanced questions.
We have to sit with them in their suffering
and allow them to wrestle with God
in the midst of it.
Yes, God will bring redemption,
but that redemption doesn't look like
all of our pain and suffering
goes away forever
and we never feel the consequences of it.
Often redemption is painstakingly slow.
Sometimes we don't even see it
on this side of creation.
Sometimes it's only redemption in eternity.
And how when we sell people a gospel
that doesn't let them wrestle or suffer,
that tries to give quick, short, easy answers
to the most complex questions in their life,
no wonder that they're walking out the doors in droves.
We need to learn to be a people
who create space for people to wrestle,
to ask questions,
because the grand narrative of Scripture
will hold up to the test.
We can hold two truths in tension.
We can cling to God in faith,
looking for and partnering with Him
in His redemption
while continuing to wrestle
and question and doubt
with tears in our eyes.
All right.
We can see that redemption play out.
Spoiler alert.
We're gonna read the end of the book of Ruth.
And then for the rest of the series,
we'll come back and work our way through.
Sound good?
All right.
Ruth chapter four.
Verse 16.
So Ruth and Naomi,
you remember after I rambled a lot
that we ended the verse
by seeing Ruth and Naomi,
two widows,
Ruth, Naomi, and Orpah,
three widows,
alone in Moab
with pretty much almost certain death.
Orpah decides to stay in Moab
while Ruth and Naomi come back to Israel.
And lots of things happen
that we're gonna talk about
for the next couple of weeks,
but this is how it ends in verse 16.
Ruth, Naomi,
widows with no hope for a future,
a struggle for food,
a struggle for family,
a struggle for life itself.
We read this in verse 16.
Naomi took the baby,
a new baby,
cuddled him to her breast
and she cared for him
as if he were her own.
The neighboring women said,
now at last,
Naomi has a son again
and they named him Obed.
He became the father of Jesse
and the grandfather of David.
At the end of verse five,
Naomi and Ruth,
they've lost everything.
There's no food,
no family
and they're in danger
of almost certain death.
And now at the end
of the book of Ruth,
we see Naomi
in a stable financial situation
with a new addition
to the family
and the beginning
of the genealogy of David,
which will lead to Jesus,
who is the cornerstone
of not just temporary redemption,
but temporary redemption
for individuals,
but eternal redemption
for all of Christ.
The book of Ruth begins
with Israel desperately
in need of a king
and it ends
with a genealogy
that will lead
to the everlasting throne
of David.
It starts with no food
in the house of bread
and it gives us
a shadow of the one
who will be born
in the house of bread
and declare,
I am the bread of life.
Anyone who comes to me
will never go hungry.
The book of Ruth
is the story
of the entire Bible
that God brings about
redemption
in the midst of suffering
and chaos
to anyone
who will cling
to him in faith.
It does not mean
that our lives are easy
on this side
of new creation.
It does not mean
that we will not suffer
and feel the consequences
of the chaos
of this world.
But it does mean
if we can just
cling to him
in faith,
continue to wrestle
and ask questions
that he is
and will
and will continue
to bring about redemption.
God is in the business
of bringing about
redemption.
Redemption means
to buy back.
God is inviting us
out of chaos and death
and into the abundance
of life.
It's beautiful
but it's still messy
on this side of heaven.
We still feel
the consequences
of living in a broken world
even when we've been
redeemed out of one.
God will bring redemption
in the midst of chaos
and suffering,
chaos that we've brought
about on ourselves
and chaos
that have been brought
on us by others.
And this redemption
is for anyone.
Anyone.
And that is one
of the most incredible truths
that we are gonna discover
throughout the book of Ruth.
Anybody who has been told
by their friends
who are out on Christianity
that the God of the Old Testament
is nothing like Jesus?
Let's just step back
for a second
and realize that there is
a book in the Bible
that is named
after a Gentile
idolatrous woman.
Redemption,
God's redemption
is for everyone
who will cling
to him in faith.
Everyone.
Naomi needs redemption.
Ruth needs redemption.
And as we'll see,
Boaz,
who is a wealthy person
of power
in his culture,
needs the redemption
of God.
It's for all of us.
But in order for us
to receive it,
we have to cling
to him in faith.
As we were singing
and worship this morning,
I was just thinking
about my message
and I had this vision
of the woman
who was struggling
with bleeding
for 12 years.
And she's tried everything.
Every story,
every doctor,
every scientific answer,
every mystic answer,
she's tried everything.
And none of it is work.
She says,
all right,
I've got enough energy
to try one more thing.
Where else can I go?
What else am I gonna do?
And she finds
where Jesus is
in the midst of a crowd
and who knows
what difficult things
she had to do
to get in a position
where she could just
reach out
and touch his garment.
And I just feel like
this morning,
I need to say
to some of us
in the room
that if that's all
the faith you can muster,
if you've tried
everything else,
if you've looked
for answers
to your questions
in any other place,
that if you can
just muster up
enough faith
to reach out
and grab his garment,
you will be faithful
to redeem
and to restore
and to renew
and to bring out
about hope
and healing
in the midst
of your suffering
and struggle.
This is the invitation
of the grand narrative
of Scripture,
the story that makes sense
of each one of our stories.
We were created
for a relationship
with God,
for abundance in life
and instead
we chose
rebellion
and chaos.
But God
is in the process
of redemption
and we are invited
to experience
and participate
in that process.
It's a process
that seems
painstakingly slow
to us
but not to God.
We think God
is being slow
or totally absent
letting good people
suffer unnecessarily
but in reality
he is being patient
giving all of us
repeated opportunities
to hear, see
and respond
to the invitation
of faith.
Maybe you're here
and you've never
made this decision
to cling to Jesus
in faith.
I'd consider you.
That's not right.
We've been here
too long, people.
I'd encourage you
to consider
Jesus this morning.
He is the author
and perfecter
of the story
that makes sense
of all of our stories
and he is the one
you've been looking for.
Maybe you're like
a limeleck
and you'd say
Jesus is the Lord
of my life
but if I'm honest
the decisions
that I make
when my back
is against the wall
don't represent
that reality.
Maybe this morning
is an invitation
for you to
acknowledge the ways
in which your
decision making
does not line up
with your spiritual identity
that you'd repent
and turn back to God.
Or maybe you're here
and you're more like
Naomi
and you'd say
the primary experience
of your life
is suffering
and you're not even sure
you really want
to cling to God
in faith.
If that's you
I would say
be honest with God
about your questions
and your struggles
and find a friend
like Ruth
who you trust
that can help you
on your faith journey.
God will bring redemption
in the midst of chaos
and suffering
to anyone
anyone
and I mean anyone
who clings to him
in faith.
Let's pray.
Father we thank you
for your word
for the stories
that you have preserved
for us
by the power
of your Holy Spirit
in the language
of real people
with real pens
and real paper
telling real stories
of your redemption.
God we want to
we want to cling
to you in faith.
We want to see
this process
of redemption
happen in our own lives
and in our communities
and around the world.
We want suffering
and chaos to end.
We want new creation.
No more sorrow
no more pain
no more mourning.
God until that day comes
may we look for ways
to participate
in your redemption.
God may this group
of people
in this room
be a people
that surrender
to you
and see
life and abundance
happen
in the midst
of the brokenness
of the world
around us
that we might be
a light
to the world
a city
on a hill.
in Jesus name
I pray
amen.
Tell Michelle
I'm sorry parents
go in peace
we'll see you
next week.
God bless you.
Thank you.